Finding Aid for Richard D. T. Hollister Papers 1887-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard D. T. Hollister Papers 1887-1960
Hollister, Richard Dennis Teall, 1878-
851535 Aa 2 AC
Professor of speech and drama at the University of Michigan, 1904-1949; papers document Hollister's teaching and development of the speech and drama programs at the university, include correspondence, course material and lecture notes, papers and photographs relating to dramatic productions, and some family material.
2.3 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received in several accessions over the years 1957 to 1963, the majority being donated by Richard Hollister (donor no. 1024 ).
The collection is open for research.
Richard Dennis Teall Hollister, born October 26, 1878, in Green Oak Township, Michigan (near Brighton), graduated from Ann Arbor High School in 1898. He went on to receive an A.B. degree in chemistry and mathematics from the University of Michigan in 1902. In 1903 he received his A.M. degree in Oratory, English and Education, and in 1936 his Ph.D., both from the University of Michigan. While a student, he participated in track and baseball and was president of the Student Christian Association. He was also a member of the Toastmasters Club and the Michigan Schoolmasters Club and was elected to Michigamua.
Hollister was an assistant in oratory during the 1902/1903 school year at the University of Michigan, followed by one year as the head of the Department of Public Speaking at the Michigan Military Academy. He was in charge of oratory during the 1904 summer session at the University of Michigan and made instructor the same year. He was named assistant professor of public speaking in 1912 and associate professor of speech in 1920. Subjects taught over the years included elocution, extempore speaking, debating, study of great orators, forensic masterpieces, Shakespearean reading, interpretative reading, and advanced public speaking. Hollister taught the university's first course in play production in 1915 and directed its first public play ("The Servant in the House"). He remained within the department, later known as the Department of Speech, from 1904 through 1949. During this time he also taught summer session courses at other institutions including the University of California, University of Southern California, Louisiana State University, State University of Iowa, University of Kentucky, and Northwestern University.
In addition to teaching, Hollister organized the Lyceum Club, an organization of advanced students who gave lectures in different towns around the state. He also managed local oratory and debate contests and trained student orators for intercollegiate contests. The climax of this work was a trip with the varsity debate team to England in 1926, in which his protégés won four out of their five debates with representatives of English universities. Hollister also directed amateur plays. In 1905 he spent three months filling a mission pulpit. By 1908 he was back in charge of oratory at the University of Michigan. He also wrote numerous books and articles during his career.
Hollister married Jessie I. Holmes in 1906 (A.B. Michigan 1905). The Hollisters had three children: son Richard and daughters Ruth (A.B. 1931, A.M. 1932) and Marian (Arch. 1937). Professor Hollister died February 4, 1968, in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
The Richard D. T. Hollister papers, 1887-1960, document his career as a professor of speech and theater and the development of the Department of Speech and theatrical productions at the University of Michigan. Correspondents include: Thomas E. Black, Marion L. Burton, John R. Effinger, Edward H. Kraus, J. Raleigh Nelson, James M. O'Neill, Theodore Roosevelt, Alexander G. Ruthven, and Thomas C. Trueblood. The Hollister papers are divided into three series; Richard D. T. Hollister, Hollister family and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Fenton High School (Mich.); Hollister, Richard Dennis Teall, 1878-; Lyceum Club (University of Michigan); Michigan Military Academy.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.; University of Michigan. Extension Service.; University of Michigan. Oratorical Association.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Debates and debating--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Black, Thomas E.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.; Hollister, Emily Jane Green, 1839-1918.; Hollister, Mary Chamberlin.; Kraus, Edward Henry, 1875-1973; Nelson, J. Raleigh (Joseph Raleigh); O'Neill, James Milton, 1881-1970.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Sarett, Lew, 1888-1954.; Trueblood, Thomas C. (Thomas Clarkson), 1856-1951.
Visual Materials - Subjects:
Theaters--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Lyceum Club (University of Michigan); Photographs.; Players Club (University of Michigan); Toastmasters Club (University of Michigan); Theatrical productions.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Speech.; University of Michigan--Dramatics.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Richard D. T. Hollister
  The Richard D. T. Hollister series (2 linear ft.), includes lectures, manuscripts, news clippings, and correspondence relating to the activities of Hollister and the speech department's courses, lectures, recitals, debating team, and dramatics. Included within this series is Hollister's master's thesis The Time Spirit in Oratory and data used for his Ph.D. study Relation between Hand and Voice Impulse Movements.
  - Article on the beginning course, reprint and manuscript, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Autobiography, "My Yesterday" 1957 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketch circa 1910 (Box 1)
  - Class materials (may include notes, examinations, assignments, and/or other miscellanea)
    - Bible Reading I 1910 (Box 1)
    - Interpretive Reading 1911-1930 (Box 1)
    - Oral English 1916-1925 (Box 1)
    - Oral Interpretation 1926-1930 (Box 1)
    - Oral Reading 1925, undated (Box 1)
    - Oratory 1 1912 (Box 1)
    - Oratory 2
      - Lecture notes 1906-1920 (Box 1)
      - Notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Platform Principles, undated (Box 1)
    - Play Production 14a
      - 1915-1920 (Box 1)
      - 1921-1930 (Box 1)
    - Play Reading assignments 1906-1920 (Box 1)
    - Public speaking 1906-1915 (Box 1)
    - Speech 31 1936-1940 (Box 1)
    - Speech 42, oral interpretation, Tennyson and Browning, examinations
      - 1931-1935 (Box 1)
      - 1936-1945 (Box 1)
    - Speech 43
      - Assignments 1931-1940 (Box 1)
      - Notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Speech 63, Course outline 1926-1930 (Box 1)
    - Speech 115 1926-1930 (Box 1)
    - Speech 137, radio reading and dramatics 1939 (Box 1)
    - Theory of Expression 1916-1920 (Box 1)
    - Vocalization, undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings, programs, etc. concerning:
    - Lectures and recitals, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Speeches
      - 1906-1910 (Box 1)
      - 1911-1915 (Box 1)
      - 1921-1927 (Box 1)
      - 1941-1945, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1911-1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1926-1930, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1931-1935 (Box 2)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1941-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951-1960 (Box 2)
  - Data for Ph.D. study, "Relation between Hand and Voice Impulse Movements" (Box 2)
  - Debate briefs, undated (Box 2)
  - Debating notes, speeches, bibliography 1906-1910, undated (Box 2)
  - Debating Team, England trip 1926 (Box 2)
  - Debating team and oratory lists, 1916-1930; also constitution of Michigan, Indiana, Ohio Debating League (Box 2)
  - Dramatic Association of the University: reports and notes 1916-1925 (Box 2)
  - Dramatics committee schedule of plays 1923 (Box 2)
  - Interpretative Arts Society: programs, clippings, etc. 1931-1940 (Box 2)
  - Lecture(s) on:
    - Education 1909 (Box 2)
    - Hamlet 1909 (Box 2)
    - Macbeth and Julius Caesar, 1910 and undated (Box 2)
    - Shakespeare 1916-1925, undated (Box 2)
    - Success undated (Box 2)
    - Tennyson's Maude undated (Box 2)
    - The Rivals 1911-1915 (Box 2)
  - Lyceum Club papers and correspondence
    - 1906-1915 (Box 2)
    - 1956-1960, undated (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts
    - Effective declamation 1913 (Box 2)
    - Oral interpretation undated (Box 2)
    - Time patterns of impulse movements in the oral interpretation of literature undated (Box 2)
  - Memos and estimates on alteration of stage at University Hall 1926 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea 1903-1945, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes and briefs for analysis and brief making 1906-1915 (Box 2)
  - Notes and manuscript on History of Play Production at the University of Michigan undated (Box 2)
  - Notes and reports of committee on Evaluation of Faculty Service 1936-1945 (Box 2)
  - Notes of lectures by B. A. Hinsdale circa 1900 (Box 2)
  - Notes, clippings and miscellanea on University College plan 1928 (Box 2)
  - Outline for book on debating undated (Box 2)
  - Papers
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1887-1910 (Box 2)
    - concerning Angell Hall speech rooms 1916-1925 (Box 2)
  - Plans for Interpretive Arts Club and/or division of Platform and Theatre Arts, 1926-1930 (Box 2)
  - Plans for reorganization of Literary College 1926-1955 (Box 2)
  - Play Production, producible plays 1911-1920 (Box 2)
  - Play: "The Great Galeoto", by José Echegaray (Box 2)
  - Players Club constitution and notes (Box 2)
  - Plays produced by Hollister 1909-1926 (Box 2)
  - Public recitals, oral interpretation 1906-1925 (Box 2)
  - Questions for debate 1906-1920, undated (Box 2)
  - Speech Department Controversy 1926-1930
    - Notes for committee meetings (Box 2)
    - Statements, charts, etc. (Box 2)
  - Speech notes 1916-1940 (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    - Audience Unknown
      - 1911-1915, undated (Box 2)
      - 1916-1920, undated (Box 2)
      - 1921-1930, undated (Box 2)
    - Before church groups 1906-1920 (Box 3)
    - Common faults in college orations 1917 (Box 3)
    - Dramatic festivals and contests undated (Box 3)
    - Faculty judging and judging contests undated (Box 3)
    - Public school and community dramatics 1921 (Box 3)
    - Radio talks 1911-1940, undated (Box 3)
  - Summer teaching, bulletins, publicity, etc. 1936-1940 (Box 3)
  - Thesis: The Time Spirit in Oratory 1905 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook of plays produced by Hollister 1909-1926 (Volume AC)
- Hollister Family
  Hollister Family series (two folders), consists of the diary (1881-1911) of Emily Hollister, Richard Hollister's mother. Also included in this series are family letters,1846-1884, most from Mary (Chamberlin) Hollister to her daughter Jeannette, others from Mary's siblings and their children.
  - Emily Hollister diary 1888-1911 (Box 3)
    (original & typescript)
  - Mary Hollister and Jeanette Hollister letters 1846-1884 (Box 3)
- Photographs, 1909-1926, undated
  The Photographs series (five folders, 1909-1926 and undated), consists of photographs of play productions, which were removed from a scrapbook. Also included within this series are formal society photos, including the Players Club, Toastmasters Club, and Lyceum Club.
  - Plays (Box 3)
    (removed from scrapbook)
    - 1909-1920 (Box 3)
    - 1921-1923 (Box 3)
    - 1924-1926 (Box 3)
    - Undated (Box 3)
  - Societies (Box 3)
    (include Players Club, Toastmasters Club, and Lyceum Club)